Guide to the Grace Linton Cook Papers about W. J. Linton
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Grace Linton Cook Papers about W. J. Linton
1840-1936
GEN MSS 1406
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.71
4 boxes
Cook, Grace Linton, 1881-1975
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Linton Family Papers, 1855-1919. II. W. J. Linton Collection, 1840-1895.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Estate of Grace Linton Cook, 1980.
Grace Linton Cook (1881-1975)
Grace Harriet Linton was born in New Haven, Connecticut, on September 9, 1881, the daughter of Edmund Wade Linton (1848-1918) and Carrie E. Callender Linton (1855-1936), and the granddaughter of the British wood engraver W. J. Linton. After her marriage to Harry E. Cook (1881-1960) she lived in Stratford, Connecticut, and died in Bridgeport, Connecticut, on July 9, 1975.
W. J. Linton (1812-1897)
The British wood engraver, author, historian, printer, publisher, and political activist William James Linton was born in London on December 7, 1812. He immigrated to New York in 1866 and in 1867 settled at Appledore, a small farm and cottage in Hamden, Connecticut, just north of New Haven. There he founded his Appledore Private Press and wrote and printed several of his most notable works including The Masters of Wood-Engraving (1886). Linton died in New Haven, at the home of his daughter Margaret Linton Mather, on December 29, 1897.
Linton was married twice, first in 1837 to Laura Wade (1809-1838) and after the death of her sister (and his common-law wife) Emily Wade in 1856, to the author Eliza Lynn (1822-1898). Emily Wade was the mother of Linton's seven children: William Wade (1839/1841-1892), Emily (born ca. 1845), Lancelot (ca. 1846-1863), Edmund Wade (1848-1918), Margaret Wade (1851-1943), Ellen Wade (1852-1938), and Eliza (died 1856). Three of the children, Edmund, Margaret, and Ellen (known as "Nellie"), accompanied Linton to America, became naturalized citizens, and settled in New Haven.
Scope and Contents
The collection primarily consists of material by or about W. J. Linton, including some of his writings and examples of his engravings which wereas inherited or collected by his granddaughter Grace Linton Cook. Also present is a small group of personal papers of Cook, her father Edmund Wade Linton, and her aunt Ellen ("Nellie") Linton.
Series I, Family Papers, contains three family letters and a group of family papers that include a Linton biography and a scrapbook of Linton's engravings compiled by a young Grace Cook, a set of W. J. Linton calendars created by Ellen Linton, and some early material related to Edmund Wade Linton. Also present is an short story published by W. J. Linton's third wife E. Lynn Linton, and a series of obituaries and other posthumous tributes to, W. J. Linton.
Series II, W. J. Linton Collection, contains manuscript and printed material written or published by Linton, some of which have his autograph edits. It is evenly divided between work created in England, both in London and in the Lake District, and work created after he moved to New Haven in the mid-1860s. Also filed here are writings by others about Linton; at the end of the series are three issues of journals issued during his lifetime but have no obvious connection to Linton.
Wood-engravers -- England; Wood-engravers -- United States; Wood-engraving -- 19th century; Wood engravings (prints) -- England -- 19th century; Wood-engravers -- England -- 19th century; Wood-engravers -- United States -- 19th century; Cook, Grace Linton, 1881-1975; Linton, E. Lynn (Elizabeth Lynn), 1822-1898; Linton, Edmund Wade, 1848-1918; Linton, W. J. (William James), 1812-1897
- Linton Family Papers, 1855–1936; Series I; 2.08; 2 boxes
  Arrangement
  Organized into three subseries: Correspondence, Personal Papers, and Publications.
  - Correspondence
    - Letter from Edmund Wade Linton to Grace Linton Cook, 1906 October 23 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letters from William Wade Linton to Grace Linton Cook, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Personal Papers
    - "Biography of William James Linton" by Grace Linton Cook; autograph manuscript, 1899 November 2 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Scope and Contents
      Written as a school paper.
    - "Farewell entertainment program by Ellen Linton; autograph manuscript, 1873 February 28 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Inscribed "For Edmund, from Nellie."
    - "W. J. Linton calendars" by Ellen Linton; autograph manuscript, 1917–1919 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Manuscript calendars featuring W. J. Linton's poetry, issued as Christmas tokens for family members.
    - "Wood-engraving / W. J. Linton", 1896 December (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Scrapbook created by Grace Linton Cook, Christmas 1896
    - School notebook kept by Edmund Wade Linton while at West House School, 1861–1863 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Contains accounting exercises, financial records, and German exercises.
    - Sketchbook with graphite and watercolor drawings by Edmund Wade Linton, 1869–1877 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Hand-lettered visiting card of Edmund Wade Linton, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Photographs of Edmund Wade Linton and Carrie E. Callender Linton, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "A Pagan's Outlook", undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Manuscript poem in an unidentified hand.
  - Publications
    - Juvenile Atlas (London: John C. Tacey, circa 1860) (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Cover inscribed upper right: "E. Linton 1860."
    - Selections of Poetry and Prose (New Haven: Boardman School Press, 1897) (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Contains an illustration on page 7 by Grace Linton Cook when a student at Boardman High School.
    - Linton, E. Lynn "Snowed Up with a Burglar," in Every Month 1, no. 1 (January 1869):25-39, 1869 January (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - "London as a Literary Centre," by R. R. Bowker, in Harper's New Monthly Magazine 77, no. 457 (June 1888): 2-26, 1888 June (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Features a portrait and profile of E. Lynn Linton on pages 23-25.
    - Mather, Mollie, A Little Girl's Story (Hamden: Appledore Press, 1895) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Report of the Librarian of Yale University, 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Contains description of Linton descendants' gifts to the university in 1919, on pages 7-8.
    - W. J. Linton
      - Obituary and article on Appledore, 1897, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 18)
        Contains an obituary and an article from New Haven Register
      - Obituary, 1897 December 30 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 67)
        Issue of Journal Courier, New Haven
      - Review of memorial exhibition at the Century Club, 1898 February 26 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 68)
        Page from New York Times
      - "William James Linton" by Burton J. Hendrick, in New England Magazine 18, no. 2 (April 1898): 138-157, 1898 April (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - "Belated Reverence Paid to Linton, Poet-Printer", 1931 July 5 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 69)
        Page from New Haven Register
- W. J. Linton Collection, 1840–1895; Series II; 0.63; 2 boxes
  Organized into three subseries: Personal Papers, Writings and Engravings, and Other Writings and Publications
  - Personal Papers
    - Visiting cards, engraved with address of 13, Upper Berkeley Street West, London, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Portraits of W. J. Linton, 1882, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
      Three portraits, and one photograph of Linton standing on the porch at Appledore.
    - "Death of Mr. S. G. Lynn", undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
      Copied by Linton from The Irish Canadian, vol. x, no. 9
  - Writings and Engravings (Box 2)
    Arranged in chronological order.
    - Bob Thin: a Poor-law Tale (London: J. Watson, [184-?]), circa 1845 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Advertising cards for "Mr. Honeysuckle's Store of Children's Books, 85, Hatton Garden, London", circa 1850 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Flowers, Fruits, and Leaves booklets (London: C. Honeysuckle), circa 1850 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Wild Flowers for Children, Part 1 (London: C. Honeysuckle), circa 1850 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - The English Republic: handbills and broadside advertisements, 1851 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 70)
    - "Our Tricolor" [Brantwood, Coniston, Windermere?]: [W. J. Linton?], [approximately 1850?], circa 1850 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - "Hymns", 1854 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      Booklet in wrappers with autograph title page; contains poems clipped from printed works glued to pages, with autograph headings, titles, revisions, and corrections, along with one autograph poem.
    - Pepys' pickle: a tract for the 29th of May (Brantwood, Coniston, Windermere: W. J. Linton, [1854?]), circa 1854 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - War Cries (Brantwood, Coniston, Windermere: W.J. Linton, [1854?], circa 1854 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Handbill for Pen and Pencil, An Illustrated Family Newspaper, 1855 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      Accompanied by embossed mailing envelope from the journal.
    - Brantwood Miscellany, no. 1, 1856 May (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - "To the great arbiter" [Brantwood, Coniston, Windermere]: [W. J. Linton], [approximately 1860?], circa 1860 (Box 2, Folder 33)
      A poem, signed at end: "W. J. Linton, Brantwood. Kendal Mercury, Aug. 18."
    - The Lake Country by E. Lynn Linton with illustrations by W. J. Linton (London: Smith, Elder and Company, 1864) (Box 2, Folder 34)
      Proof sheets, with autograph corrections, of engravings by Linton; accompanied by proof sheets with autograph edits by E. Lynn Linton.
    - "Fenianism and Republicanism", circa 1867 (Box 2, Folder 35)
      Autograph manuscript, signed, of a preface for Ireland for the Irish: Rhymes and Reasons Against Landlordism (New York: The American News Company, 1867).
    - "In Memory of James Watson" (London: Blakeman Jagger, 1874) (Box 2, Folder 36)
      Two copies. Printed in New York Evening Post and afterward in the Newcastle Chronicle.
    - "Mr. Joseph", 1874 December (Box 2, Folder 37)
      Autograph manuscript, signed, of a play written for Christmas entertainment at Appledore
    - England to America 1876 A New-Year's Greeting (Cambridge: Welch, Bigelow Co, 1876) (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - "The Engraver," in Scribner's Monthly 16, no. 2 (June 1878), 1878 June (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - "Slanderers", 1879 January (Box 2, Folder 40)
      A complaint by Linton that George Howell, in an article in the journal Nineteenth Century, called Gustave Paul Cluseret a Fenian and that James Knowles, the journal's editor, refused to print Linton's letter of protest. Signed at end: W. J. Linton, January 1879.
    - "Art in Engraving on Wood," in Atlantic Monthly 43, no. 260 (June 1879): 705-715, 1879 June (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - "Editorial Right: a Question of Honesty and Plain Speech", 1879 June (Box 2, Folder 42)
      Regarding Linton's experience with editors at Atlantic Monthly.
    - Translations (Hamden: Appledore Press, 1881) (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Good Counsel (Hamden: Appledore Press, 1886) (Box 2, Folder 44)
      Five copies.
    - Moralities (Hamden: Appledore Press, 1891) (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Darwiniads and "Jonah's Story" (Hamden: Appledore Press, 1892) (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - A Christmas Carol (Hamden: Appledore Press, 1893), 1893 December (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Times and Seasons (Hamden: Appledore Press, 1894) (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - "An Artist's Habitat", 1895 May (Box 2, Folder 49)
      Galley proof, with autograph and manuscript corrections, of an article that appeared in Lippincott's Monthly Magazine (May 1895).
    - "If a poor flower…", 1895 December (Box 2, Folder 50)
      Two copies.
    - "Old and Young - Mahmoud's Flight", 1895 December (Box 2, Folder 51)
      Two copies of a galley proof of Linton's poem printed in The Independent 48, no. 2459 (January 16, 1896): 26.
    - Of a Mollusc (Hamden: Appledore Press, 1895) (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Ultima Verba (Hamden: Appledore Press, 1895) (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - "Forget-me-not" (Hamden: Appledore Press), undated (Box 3, Folder 54)
      Two copies
    - "Good Lord Deliver Us", undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - "Our Fatherland (In Answer to Herwegh)", undated (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - "Times and Seasons", undated (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Clipped engravings and proof prints, undated (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Other Writings and Publications
    - A Little Book About Victories (Political Horn Book, No. 1) London: J. Watson, 1843) (Box 3, Folder 59)
      Illustrations thought to be Linton engravings.
    - "The Two Wars.--The Two Plans of War" by Joseph Mazzini, 1866 (Box 3, Folder 60)
      Galley proof from unidentified publication with Linton's autograph edits and a preface by him.
    - Newspaper clippings, 1880–1893 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - "William James Linton" by Fred G. Kitton, in English Illustrated Magazine 91, no. 8 (April 1891): 490-500, 1891 April (Box 3, Folder 62)
      With frontispiece portrait engraved by W. Biscombe Gardner; issue has prospectus and order form for Linton's The Masters of Wood-Engraving, and an advertisement for Poems and Translations.
    - A Guide to Windermere and its Vicinity (Manchester: Abel Heywood and Son; London: Simpkin, Marshall Co., [1866?]) (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Scribner's Monthly Illustrated Magazine 21, no. 4 (February 1881), 1881 February (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Harper's New Monthly Magazine 80, no. 478 (March 1890), 1890 March (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Monthly Chronicle of North Country Lore & Legend, part 58 (December 1891), 1891 December (Box 3, Folder 66)